<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Beta Thinker - Random thoughts of a software engineer</title>
    <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Beta Thinker - Random thoughts of a software engineer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 16:03:38 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://betathinker.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Streaming vs batching</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/streaming_vs_batching_processing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/streaming_vs_batching_processing/</guid>
      <description>Pros of streaming:
Lower latency Cons of streaming:
Harder to achieve good throughput: processing a bunch of data point in a batching fashion can usually take advantage of natural hardware support for batching like: CPU: SIMD, vectorization, multicore parallelism Memory/Disk: read/write a big chunk of data at once has better throughput than read/write a bunch of small chunks Network: sending/receiving a group of large packets at once is more efficient than sending/receiving a bunch of small packets Harder operation-wise to run a production streaming system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Never let a good crisis go to waste</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/never_let_a_good_crisis_go_to_waste/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/never_let_a_good_crisis_go_to_waste/</guid>
      <description>The older I am, the more I appreciate the wisdom of the quote &amp;ldquo;Never let a good crisis go to waste.&amp;rdquo; Individual people, small group, large group, a company, a society, all of them wants some small change to keep life exciting but hate large change. Meaningful change so so rarely happen from within even when it is needed. Like the proverbial &amp;ldquo;slow boiling frog,&amp;rdquo; people won&amp;rsquo;t make significant change if their situation deteriorate slowly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Utopia and dystopia</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/utopia_and_dystopia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/utopia_and_dystopia/</guid>
      <description>I have been wondering for a while if exists, what utopia would look like. There is no exact definition of utopia but I define it as a state in which everyone is always happy. I haven&amp;rsquo;t come to a firm conclusion but my current belief is that utopia cannot exist because of a few fundamental characteristics of human nature:
Human are social creature. They need to interact with other people to be happy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Money is imaginary</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/money_is_imaginary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/money_is_imaginary/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Money&amp;rdquo; is made up but its liquidity/ease of exchange has real value. &amp;ldquo;Resources&amp;rdquo; including physical, digital assets and human capital are real (stock is a claim on asset, can also be considered resources). Thus, controlling of asset and liquidity are what important.
Some implications:
When money supplies increase, liquidity increases =&amp;gt; holding resources is better, avoid having too much money and liquidity FED prints money FED decreases interest rate When money supplies decrease, liquidity decreases =&amp;gt; liquidity increases in its relative value, hold more money, have less resources * People saves lots of money, more control of resources are in hands of government and companies =&amp;gt; more investment, more production =&amp;gt; export increases People saves little money, more control of resources are in hands of people =&amp;gt; less investment, less production =&amp;gt; import increases </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What does manager do?</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/what_does_manager_do/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/what_does_manager_do/</guid>
      <description>What does manager do? What are the difference between leadership and management?
Managers&amp;rsquo; inputs are business goals and human resources. Outputs are business results. The measure of success of a manager is how well he can maximize output with the least amount of resources.
The above is the idealized version. In practices, lots of time, managers are judged by:
How well they present and make a case for their business impact than their actual impact.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should society optimize more for worker rather than consumer</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/should_society_optimize_more_for_worker_rather_than_consumer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/should_society_optimize_more_for_worker_rather_than_consumer/</guid>
      <description>Society has always consider work as a means to an end: to create some concrete product, or render some service. Would it make sense to start consider work as an end in itself?
Work by itself can produce some very important end &amp;ldquo;products&amp;rdquo; other than its concrete product or service output, such as, in order of importance:
Sense of meaning Environment for social interaction Mental exercise Physical exercise The counter argument to the above would be there are better ways than work to accomplish those goals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some potential consequences of a AI</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/some_potential_consequence_of_ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/some_potential_consequence_of_ai/</guid>
      <description>Proliferation of derivatives content and noise:
Derivatives arts like music, visual arts, writing content will be abundant and cheap. Lots of low-level people who make &amp;ldquo;mechanical&amp;rdquo; arts will be replaced by AI. More concentration of art market: The number of no-name digital artists, musicians, copywriters will decrease. The high-level artists whose main value proposition is their brands will be even more powerful since they can crank out content under their brand name more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why software engineering is a low status job</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_software_engineering_is_a_low_status_job/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_software_engineering_is_a_low_status_job/</guid>
      <description>Recently I have been sensing that software engineering is a low status job. Even though the popularity and income potential of software engineering is growing quickly, the social status of software engineers still seem somewhat low. For an average Joe, a software engineering doesn&amp;rsquo;t have quite the same social cachet as other typical prestigious jobs in society like a doctor, a lawyer, a management consultant, an investment banker,
I will try to go through some potential reasons why software engineering is a relatively low status job compared to its current earning potential</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Judeo Christian</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/judeo_christian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/judeo_christian/</guid>
      <description>It is a common conception that the US is founded or heavily influenced by Judeo Christianity and Anglo Saxon culture. However, what exactly does that mean? The term usually conjures up some image of individualism, classical liberalism, Christian religion. Those are vague and don&amp;rsquo;t sufficiently explain what concrete characteristics of American culture it brings about.
To start, let&amp;rsquo;s list out some characteristics of Judeo Christianity and Anglo Saxon culture:
Monotheism, concept of one God, omnipotent god, human-.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some behavioral differences between educated American and Vietnamese</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/some_behaviorial_differences_between_american_and_vietnamese/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/some_behaviorial_differences_between_american_and_vietnamese/</guid>
      <description>Some differences that I observed exist between educated, smart Vietnamese and Americans:
American read and, more importantly, write books more. Vietnamese are more flexible and adhoc when dealing with problems. I doubt that a similar version of the US supreme court, in which justices engage in highly technical, rigorously logical subtleties of each word in a constitution, can exists. Deep down, Vietnamese don&amp;rsquo;t like inflexibility and rationality in social decisions. Most American are also like that but there exists some segment of elite American intellectuals who value and believe in rationality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some of my behaviors</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/some_of_my_behaviors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/some_of_my_behaviors/</guid>
      <description>A collections of my own behaviors that I want to note down:
Don&amp;rsquo;t like answering fact questions e.g what happened, who did what, how it happened. Prefer answering opinion/judgement questions e.g what do you think about event A, person B, idea C, action D Think and judge more than do and act. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KTLO, optimization, and foundation engineering work</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/ktlo_optimization_and_foundation_engineering_work/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/ktlo_optimization_and_foundation_engineering_work/</guid>
      <description>It occurs to me today that there are broadly three types of engineering works with respect to how they contribute to the product of a tech company:
Keep-the-light-on (KTLO): these are works to keep the product running, not changing it. Usually, they include oncall, small refactoring work to reduce internal technical debts.
Product optimization: these are the types of work that locally optimizes the existing product at the margin. They make the product better, more scalable, performant, and reliable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why a small team of great engineers can be extremely productive</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_a_small_team_of_great_engineers_can_be_extremely_productive/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_a_small_team_of_great_engineers_can_be_extremely_productive/</guid>
      <description>I have worked at companies of many different sizes: from giants like Microsoft with more than 100k employees to startups like Vise with 100s employees, and everything in between, Google with tens of thousands of employees, Two Sigma, and Airtable with ~1-2k employees. From my experience, I can see why a small startup with much fewer but great engineers than larger companies can effectively compete against them. Here are some rough estimate to why:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What makes a person interesting</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/what_make_a_person_interesting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/what_make_a_person_interesting/</guid>
      <description>Recently, a younger friend asked me &amp;ldquo;What do you think makes a person interesting?&amp;rdquo; What an interesting question! For context, a few weeks ago, I suggested to her that becoming interesting is a more worthy personal goal than becoming impressive. When I gave that advice, it seemed rather natural to me and didn&amp;rsquo;t require much explanation. It came from my own personal experience meeting people. Interesting people are often more &amp;ldquo;interesting&amp;rdquo; than lots of &amp;ldquo;supposedly-impressive&amp;rdquo; people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to make software run faster</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/how_to_make_software_run_faster/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/how_to_make_software_run_faster/</guid>
      <description>After almost a decade working as a professional software engineer, I have seen that there are only a few fundamental levers that an engineer can use to make software more performant, either lower latency or higher through. I&amp;rsquo;d like to list them here and include tradeoff involving with each:
Pattern 1: Use faster or more hardware:
Common practices: Upgrade CPU, memory, network equipment, use custom ASIC, use more machines, use the cloud.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is US&#39;s low life expectancy a blessing in disguise?</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/is_us_low_life_expectancy_a_blessing_in_disguise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/is_us_low_life_expectancy_a_blessing_in_disguise/</guid>
      <description>I recently stumbled upon an interesting article explaining why life expectancy in the US is lower than in other rich countries. My takeaways are that healthcare quality is far from the main culprit. The main ones in decreasing order of impact are:
Smoking: This is mostly culture. The US used to smoke a lot more than other countries but peaked earlier. Given the lag of two to three decades between peak of smoking and peak of smoking mortality, hopefully, the US&amp;rsquo;s smoking mortality rate will come down to the same level as other countries soon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weaknesses of United States</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/united_states_weaknesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2022 17:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/united_states_weaknesses/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strengths of United States</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/united_states_strengths/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/united_states_strengths/</guid>
      <description>Nature &amp;gt; Culture &amp;gt; Political / Institution &amp;gt; Economy / Military &amp;gt; Global Power
Nature:
Best geographic: facing 2 oceans, large size, tons of natural resources, diverse climate, diverse natural wonders IQ: https://www.worlddata.info/iq-by-country.php. The US is relatively high but not the highest. However, it probably has some of the highest IQ individuals, # individuals in the top 1%. Culture
Judeo - Christianity Anglo-saxon Lack of guilt from colonialism (but slavery is a big one) Liberty, individualism, openness Capacity to attract, absorb, assimilate large immigration Export culture, soft power Institution:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why declining population is bad</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_declining_population_is_bad/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_declining_population_is_bad/</guid>
      <description>Recently, there has been a lot of online discussions happening about falling birth rate, under population and whether it is a blessing or a curse. The source of these hot debates was, of course, Elon Musk. Throughout the years, Elon has stated on multiple occasions that he was concerned with low birth rate, and that civilization is going to crumble without more children. Many online voices questioned his claim. Some do not think that declining birthrate is an issue given that the world population is now close to 8 billion as of 2022.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a build system</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/what_is_a_build_system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/what_is_a_build_system/</guid>
      <description>Related: dependency management
Input:
Code, configuration, documentation, binaries, &amp;hellip; (literal any file) File specifying 3rd party dependencies Environment variables Side-effect: Run unit test, lint Output: Binary files and anything that are needed to run the software Documentation Goal:
Avoid one-off way to build different projects
Define a set of rule to run to produce artifacts
Features
How is the rule defined?
How to detect change?
Generate different artifacts: production, debug, local, (architecture, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflection on buying townhouse in New York</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/reflection_on_buying_townhouse_in_new_york/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 17:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/reflection_on_buying_townhouse_in_new_york/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflection on my time at a fintech startup</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/reflection_on_my_time_at_a_fintech_startup/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/reflection_on_my_time_at_a_fintech_startup/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why religion is important</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_religion_is_important/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_religion_is_important/</guid>
      <description>https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1069397103037002003</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moral should be means to an end, not the end itself</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/moral_should_be_means_to_an_end/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/moral_should_be_means_to_an_end/</guid>
      <description>https://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/introduction/endinitself.shtml#:~:text=The%20word%20%22end%22%20in%20this,human%20has%20value%20in%20itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why learning humanities is important</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_learning_humanities_is_important/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_learning_humanities_is_important/</guid>
      <description>https://scholars-stage.org/the-fall-of-history-as-a-major-and-as-a-part-of-the-humanities/
https://conversationswithtyler.com/episodes/marc-andreessen/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why networking is so hard</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_networking_so_hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_networking_so_hard/</guid>
      <description>2 characteristics of networking: Distance and heterogeneity
Making the below problem harder compare to many other computer system components:
Performance: throughput, latency Performance requirement is real so many optimizations are needed. Making the real world implementation of most networking components extra complicated. Reliability Compatibility So many abstraction layer to solve the problem of Lack of control on so many component of the system Security Distance, lack of control, heterogeneity, lots of abstraction makes the issue of security much harder Because networking usually has to deal with transferring information over a much longer distance compared to other components in a computer system like CPU, GPU, memory, the above problems become much harder.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Y chromosome and Son Preference</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/son_preference_and_y_chromosome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/son_preference_and_y_chromosome/</guid>
      <description>Today, a question suddenly popped into my head: Does the preference for sons common in many cultures have anything to do with the fact that the Y chromosome passes virtually unchanged from father to son?
Many cultures around the world such as Chinese and Indian prefer sons over daughters. I am not a sociologist so I do not pretend to know if the historical cause of this phenomenon has been adequately explained or not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcast Takeaways: Sam Bankman-Fried - Creating a Perfect Market</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/review_sam_bankman_fried_on_perfect_market/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/review_sam_bankman_fried_on_perfect_market/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR: My biggest takeaway is that cryptocurrency can potentially succeed because it can innovate without all the legacy system and intermediaries holding it back. Existing financial system doesn&#39;t have that luxury. It has nothing to do with technical feasibility. It has everything to do with legacy and momentum, a classic story of disruption.
ADHD as I am, I dislike listening to podcasts. The medium conveys information at a slower speed than what I can achieve with a written article.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Coaching Habit</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/review_coaching_habit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/review_coaching_habit/</guid>
      <description>Since I became a Tech Lead Manager, I have been holding weekly 1:1s with my reports. While I had unofficially acted as a TLM for sometime now, the formality of my new title brought a whole new sense of responsibility. At the beginning, whenever my reports came to me with an issue, I felt an urge to come up with a perfect answer. &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s the point of me being manager if I could not solve my reports&amp;rsquo; issues?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to advance convervatism</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/how_to_advance_conservatism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/how_to_advance_conservatism/</guid>
      <description>This post serves as a growing deposit of ideas on how to advance conservatism in the US and the world
Macro (Being a multiplier source):
Start a successful organization such as media, social media company, politics strategy consulting, think tank promoting conservatism. Produce impactful culture: successful book, blog, social media channels Major donation with influence to cultural, social institutions such as media, universities, and significant politicians. Build a system to influence people at a city, national or worldwide level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I hate progressive ideas</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_i_hate_progressive_ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_i_hate_progressive_ideas/</guid>
      <description>This post serves as a place for me to distill my thoughts of why I dislike progressive ideas
Put equality of outcome as the single highest value to drive all decision Sacrifice liberty Sacrifice justice (equal of treatment) Willing to bring the good, the beauty, the smart, the great down </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is war necessary</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_war_is_necessary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/why_war_is_necessary/</guid>
      <description>With the recent invasion of Ukraine by Russian forces, people in Western and many Asian countries are united in condemning it.
War is necessary. War is just an extreme form of competition.
Advance humanity. Technology comes from war. Unite people at least on one side. There is no real collaboration without real competition. There is no extreme collaboration without extreme competition a.k.a war. War or a credible threat of war makes life more exciting, reminding people of the value of life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Concurrency in Go</title>
      <link>http://betathinker.com/posts/review_concurrency_in_go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 16:03:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://betathinker.com/posts/review_concurrency_in_go/</guid>
      <description>I recently finished reading the book &amp;ldquo;Concurrency in Go&amp;rdquo; by Katherine Cox-Buday. It is a relatively short book. A focused read can finish it in a few days. The content is relatively basic, converting a mix of concurrency fundamentals and specific patterns commonly found in Go concurrent code. Overall, for someone who is new to Go concurrency primitives, the book provides a good review.
A couple of new ideas that I learnt from the books are:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
